A Guide to the Papers of Frances A. Hellebrandt
Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
The Frances A. Hellebrandt Collection 1944 - 1951
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Va.
87/Jul/34
.8 Linear Ft.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Collection was received as a gift from Dr. Suzanne Hirt
Biographical/Historical Information
Frances Anna Hellebrandt was born 26 Aug, 1901 in Chicago, Illinois. Being good at science, she earned a BA in Physical Education and a MD from the University of Wisconsin by 1929. Hellebrandt held several faculty positions in Anatomy and Physiology at Wisconsin before accepting a research grant at the Clinic for Sportsmen at Charles University in Prague, Czechoslovakia from 1937-38.
She returned to Wisconsin and began to specialize in physical rehabilitation. By 1943, she had become chairman of the physical therapy department at Wisconsin. Due to the growing need for physical rehabilitation as solders return from the war, the Woman's Army Corps selected Wisconsin as a site for emergency physical therapy training. In 1944, Hellebrandt accepted a position to head the newly created Baruch Center for Physical Medicine at the Medical College of Virginia.
Hellebrandt brought most of her staff with her and founded a degree program in physical medicine at MCV, the first such facility in the South. After consolidating the department in South Hospital, Hellebrandt worked to make the Baruch Center the rehabilitation center for the State of Virginia. Hellebrandt returned to Chicago in 1951 to serve as professor and chair of physical medicine at the University of Illinois. Due to declining health, she retired in 1955. In 1957, finding retirement not to her liking, she started as a visiting lecturer, and then resumed a professorship at Wisconsin until her second retirement in 1964. She was awarded emeritus status that same year.
Hellebrandt authored over 150 scientific papers and served on the editorial board of the Journal of Applied Physiology, and American Journal of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation. Along with Prof. L. Kelso, she created several research tools and devices still in use today. She served as a Trustee for the Easter Seals Research Foundation, and received the Anderson Award from the American Association of Health, Physical Education and Recreation. The American Physiological Society's tum Suden/Hellebrandt Award is named in her honor.
Hellebrandt died 02 February, 1992 at the age of 90.
Scope and Content
The collection focuses on Hellebrandt's work with the Baruch Center for Physical Medicine. It contains annual reports, course descriptions, and documents related to the operation of the Center. Also included are several reprints of articles written by Hellebrandt and her staff on the subject of physical medicine. The collection does not contain any information regarding Hellebrandt's research or work apart from the Center.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by subject.
Contents List
- Official Documentation
  This series contains annuals reports, curriculum plans, course outlines and the organization of the Baruch Center of Physical Medicine on the campus of the Medical College of Virginia.
  - School of Physical Therapy - Master Book 1944 - 1963 (Folder 1.1)
    This is a collection of items bound together containing the curriculum and academy course requirements. Items included are as follows:
    - Medical College of Virginia School of Physical Therapy Catalog 1960 - 1962 (Folder 1.1)
    - Bulletin, MCV Physical Therapy 1962/63 (Folder 1.1)
    - Bulletin, MCV Physical Therapy 1957/58 (Folder 1.1)
    - Announcements for Sessions 1958/59 (Folder 1.1)
    - Bulletin, MCV Physical Therapy undated (Folder 1.1)
    - History of the Medical College of Virginia and the Baruch Center of Physical Medicine Oct 04, 1947 (Folder 1.1)
      Orientation Course
    - Physical Therapy Training Courses (Folder 1.1)
      school curriculum
    - Factual Data for Editorial on Baruch's Contribution to Public Welfare in Virginia Oct 17, 1946 (Folder 1.1)
    - MCV Catalogue 1946-47 (Folder 1.1)
    - Technicians Training Course 1945 (Folder 1.1)
    - Physical Therapy, a Career for Men and Women April, 1948 (Folder 1.1)
      Bulletin MCV Vol. XLV No. 4
    - Physical Therapy Technician Training Course, revised. 1945 (Folder 1.1)
  - Annual Report; Baruch Center for Physical Medicine 1947 (Folder 1.2)
    This folder contains the Center's annual report. It includes committee reports, staffing concerns and vacancies, department reports as well as financial and statistical data.
  - Annual Report; Baruch Center for Physical Medicine 1950 (Folder 1.2)
    This folder contains the Center's annual report. It includes committee reports, staffing concerns and vacancies, department reports as well as financial and statistical data. It also includes a set of proposed blueprint drawings and the following article reprints:
    - Electrophoresis of the Water-Soluble Proteins of Normal and Atrophied Muscles Non-Treated and Treated by Daily Electrical Stimulation Dec 1949 (Folder 1.3)
      Fischer, Skowlund, Bowers: Archives of Physical Therapy, Vol. 30.
    - Electric Current Transients through the Human Body (Folder 1.3)
      Moore, Journal of Applied Physiology, Vol.2, No.6
    - Chemical Factors Influencing Muscular Atrophy Oct 1949 (Folder 1.3)
      Huff, Fischer: The American Journal of Physiology, Vol. 159, No. 1
    - Lower Extremity Amputation: Its Effect on the Location of the Center of Gravity of the Body as a Whole, on Postural Alignment and on Stance Stability Oct 1949 (Folder 1.3)
      Mueller, Summers: The Physical Therapy Review, Vol. 29, No. 10
    - A Useful Tool for Testing Electrotherapy Equipment Oct 1949 (Folder 1.3)
      Eubank, Houtz: The Physical Therapy Review, Vol. 29, No. 10
    - The Influence of Mecholyl and Histamine Ion Transfer On Recovery From Fatigue Sep 1949 (Folder 1.3)
      Hellebrandt, Archives of Physical Medicine, Sep 1949 Vol. 30
    - The Measure of Joint Motion. Part I, Introductory Review of the Literature Jun 1949 (Folder 1.3)
      Hellebrandt, The Physical Therapy Review, Jun 1949 Vol. 29, No. 6
    - The Measure of Joint Motion. Part III, Reliability of Goniometry Jul 1949 (Folder 1.3)
      Hellebrandt, The Physical Therapy Review, Jul 1949 Vol. 29, No. 7
    - Potassium in Denervated, Treated and Nontreated Muscle Jun 1949 (Folder 1.3)
      Fischer, Archives of Physical Medicine, Jun 1949, Vol. 30
    - Spa Therapy, Lantern Slide Demonstration Jun 1949 (Folder 1.3)
      Hellebrandt, American Medical Association Meting, Jun 1949.
    - Electrolyte Study of the Water Soluble Proteins of Normal and Atrophied Muscles Mar 1949 (Folder 1.3)
      Fischer, Federation Proceedings, Mar 1949, Vol. 8, No. 1
    - Relative Importance of the Muscle Pump in the Prevention of Gravity Shock Jan 1949 (Folder 1.3)
      Hellebrandt, The Physical Therapy Review, Jan 1949 Vol. 29, No. 1
    - The Influence of Exercise on Intragastric Pressure Apr 1949 (Folder 1.3)
      Houtz, Skowlund, The Physical Therapy Review, Apr 1949 Vol. 29, No. 4
    - The Influence of Naturally Carbonated Mineral Water on Gastric Motility and the Secretion of Hydrochloric Acid Sep 9, 1949. (Folder 1.3)
      Hellebrandt, American Congress of Physical Medicine, Sep 9, 1949.
    - Influence of Bimanual Exercise on Unilateral Work Capacity Feb 1950 (Folder 1.3)
      Hellebrandt, Journal of Applied Physiology, Feb 1950, Vol. 2, No. 8
    - Influence of Tonic Contracture upon the Composition of Mammalian Skeletal Muscle, Especially upon its Electrolyte Content March 1950 (Folder 1.3)
      Fischer, Federation Proceedings, March 1950, Vol. 9, No. 1
    - Spa Therapy Mar 1950 (Folder 1.3)
      Hellebrandt, Postgraduate Medicine, Mar 1950 Vol. 7, No. 3
    - Physical Medicine and Habilitation in the Prevention of Chronic Invalidism Apr 01 1950 (Folder 1.3)
      Hellebrandt, Journal of the American Medical Association, Apr 01 1950 Vol.142
    - Influence of Lower Extremity Amputation on Stance Mechanics Apr 29, 1950 (Folder 1.3)
      Hellebrandt, Journal of the American Medical Association, Apr 29, 1950 Vol.142.
    - New Devices for Disability Evaluation, #2 The Thumb Ergograph Apr 1950 (Folder 1.3)
      Hellebrandt, Archives of Physical Medicine, Apr 1950 Vol. 31.
    - New Devices for Disability Evaluation, #3 The Grip Ergograph Apr 1950 (Folder 1.3)
    - Research in Disability Evaluation Apr-May 1950 (Folder 1.3)
      Hellebrandt, Journal of Rehabilitation, Apr-May 1950.
  - School of Physical Therapy; Course Manual's (Folder 1.4)
    This folder contains curriculum notes as well as a course outlines for the following courses:
    - Orientation Course (Folder 1.4)
    - Problems Course (Folder 1.4)
  - School of Physical Therapy, Organization Notes. (Folder 1.5)
    This folder contains correspondence and papers regarding the founding and initial creation of the curriculum.
- Articles and Publications
  This series contains articles and publications written by Hellebrandt
  - Loose articles 1950-1962 (Folder 2.1)
    This folder contains the following articles:
    - Postgraduate Medicine Mar 1950 (Folder 2.1)
      Vol. 7, No. 3
    - Simon Baruch - Father of Hydrotherapy in America Sep 1950 (Folder 2.1)
      Presentation to the American Congress of Physical Medicine
    - Multi-career Man Makes Good May 1951 (Folder 2.1)
      Evans, Medical Economics, May 1951
    - National Hospital Day flyers May 12, 1953 (Folder 2.1)
    - Studies in Muscle Training Neuromuscular Mechanisms Jan 1960, Apr 1961, Jan 1962 (Folder 2.1)
      Hellebrandt, Physiology Branch, Office of Naval Research
  - Articles and papers written by Hellebrandt (Folder 2.2)
    This folder contains the following articles and papers written by Hellebrandt:
    - Disability Evaluation (Folder 2.2)
      Based upon, Principles and Practices of Rehabilitation by Henry Kessler, 1950.
    - The Autonomous Component of Willed Movement (Folder 2.2)
    - Evaluating The Physical Disabilities of the Cerebral Palsied Jun 1951 (Folder 2.2)
      Address given at the American Medical Association annual meeting, Jun 1951.
    - Living Anatomy Nov 1964 (Folder 2.2)
      The Wisconsin Medical Journal, Nov 1964
    - Physical Therapy Institute, Medical Direction Nov 1954 (Folder 2.2)
      Address given at the American Hospital Association meeting, Nov 1954.
  - Professional papers (Folder 2.3)
    This folder contains Hellebrandt's curriculum vitae and index of publications.
- Photographic collection
  - Photographed Artwork (Folder 3.1)
    This folder contains photographs of images, readings, charts and other media needed for print articles.
  - Photograph Collection, snapshots. (Folder 3.2)
    This folder contains snapshots of physical therapy procedures and methods. Mounted on heavy cardboard and numbered.
  - Photographic Collection (Folder 3.3)
    This folder contains photographs of the School of Physical Therapy staff and students. People listed include: Mary Lawrence, Suzanne Hirt, Dr. Ernst Fischer, Dorothy Leland, Helen Skowlund, Margaret Moore, Edith Vail, Ellen Duval, Sara Rogers, Sara Houtz, Ann Parrish, Florence Strayer, Dr. Walter Lee, Ruth Latimer, Robert Eubanks, Thelma Pederson, Ruby Scherer and Hellebrandt.
- Miscellaneous
  This series contains various items unconnected with the other series in this collection and is listed here.
  - Blueprints (Folder 4.1)
    This folder contains blueprinted plans for the school of physical therapy to be located on the 17 and 18th floor of the Medical College of Virginia's West Hospital.
  - Photocopies of historical works. (Folder 4.2)
    This folder contains photocopies of several historical works in hydrotherapy and physical medicine. Also included are photocopies of historical book covers.
  - National YMCA Health Service Clinic 1945 (Folder 4.3)
    This folder contains the program for this annual meeting. Hellebrandt was involved with the YMCA and gave three addresses at this meeting.